教授: 上节课 我们学习了
PROFESSOR: Last time, we took a look at
一个Lisp显式控制求值器
an explicit control evaluator for Lisp
它在弥合了比如Lisp或者查询语言
and that bridged the gap between all these high-level languages
一类的高级语言
like Lisp and query language all that stuff
与传统的寄存器机器之间的鸿沟
bridged the gap between that and a conventional register machine.
事实上 你可以将显式控制求值器视为
And in fact, you can think of the explicit control evaluator
比如说是一个Lisp求值器
either as, say the code for a Lisp interpreter
你希望在某些约定的寄存器机器上实现的
if you wanted to implement it in the
Lisp解释器的汇编代码#TBD
assembly language of some conventional register transfer machine,
或者 你可以把它看做是
or, if you like, you can think of it as the microcode
某台专门运行Lisp的机器的微程序
of some machine that's going to be specially designed to run Lisp.
无论是那种情况
In either case,
我们都是把一台
Nwhat we're doing is we're taking a machine
处理低级语言的机器
that speaks some low-level language
提升到能执行Lisp之类的高级语言的层次
and we're raising the machine to a high-level language like Lisp
通过编写解释器来实现
by writing an interpreter.
来看个例子
So for instance
这里 从概念上来说
here, conceptually,
是一台专用于计算阶乘的机器
here conceptually is a special purpose machine for computing factorials.
输入5 输出120
It takes in five and puts out 120.
这个专用机器实际上
And what this special purpose machine is
是一个Lisp解释器
actually a Lisp interpreter
它将自己配置为计算阶乘
that's configured itself to run factorials
因为你向它送入了一台阶乘机器的描述
because you feed into it a description of the factorial machine.
这就是解释器
So that's what an interpreter is.
它将自己配置为
It configures itself to
模拟你所输入描述的机器
emulate a machine whose description you read in.
那么 在Lisp解释器里是什么?
Now, inside the Lisp interpreter, what's that?
里面可能是通用的寄存器语言解释器
Well, that might be your general register language interpreter
它将自己配置成像Lisp解释器那样
that configures itself to behave like a Lisp interpreter
因为你输入了一系列用寄存器语言
because you put in a whole bunch of instructions
编写的指令
in register language.
这就是显式控制求值器
This is the explicit control evaluator.
它里面也有一些库
And then it also has some sort of library
由基本运算符和Lisp运算
a library of primitive operators and Lisp operations
等等要素组成
all sorts of things like that.
这是解释执行的一般策略
That's the general strategy of interpretation.
事实上 我们所做的是
And the point is, what we're doing
通过编写解释器
is we're writing an interpreter
将机器提升到我们程序所在的层次
to raise the machine to the level of the programs that we want to write.
当然 还有另外一种策略
Well, there's another strategy
这种不同的策略就是编译
a different one, which is compilation.
编译有一些不同
Compilation's a little bit different.
这里
Here--
我们可能已经实现了
here we might have produced
一个特定用途的机器
a special purpose machine for,
用来计算阶乘
for computing factorials
从某种使用寄存器语言的机器开始
starting with some sort of machine that speaks register language
但是 我们将让它执行不同的策略
except we're going to do a different strategy.
把我们的阶乘程序
We take our factorial program.
作为源代码输入编译器
We use that as the source code into a compiler.
编译器就会
What the compiler will do
把这个阶乘程序
is translate that factorial program
翻译成某种寄存器机器语言
into some register machine language.
现在它并不是Lisp的显式控制求值器
And this will now be not the explicit control evaluator for Lisp
而是某种用来计算阶乘的寄存器语言
this will be some register language for computing factorials.
这就是翻译的过程
So this is the translation of that.
它将进入某种加载器
That will go into some sort of loader
它会把这些代码
which will combine this code
和从程序库中选取的代码
with code selected from the library
比如乘法运算等 结合在一起
to do things like primitive multiplication.
随后我们将生成一个加载模块
And then we'll produce a load module
它把寄存器语言机器配置成
which configures the register language machine
一个专门用来计算阶乘的机器
to be a special purpose factorial machine.
这就是不同的策略
So that's a, that's a different strategy.
在解释中
In interpretation,
我们把
we're raising
机器提升到比如Lisp语言的层次
the machine to the level of our language, like Lisp.
而在编译中
In compilation
我们将我们的程序下降到
we're taking our program and lowering
机器语言的层次
it to the language that's spoken by the machine.
那么 这两个策略有什么区别呢?
Well, how do these two strategies compare?
编译器可以生成执行起来更有效率的代码
The compiler can produce code that will execute more efficiently.
主要原因是
The essential reason for that
如果你考虑运行中的寄存器操作
is that if you think about the register operations that are running
解释器需要生成寄存器的操作
the interpreter has to produce register operations
从原则上来讲 它需要足够通用
which, in principle, are going to be general enough
以支持任何Lisp过程的执行
to execute any Lisp procedure.
而编译器只需要
Whereas the compiler only has to worry about
生成一组特定的寄存器操作
producing a special bunch of register operations for
用来执行你所编译的那部分特定的Lisp过程
for doing the particular Lisp procedure that you've compiled.
换一种说法
Or another way to say that
解释器是一种通用的模拟器
is that the interpreter is a general purpose simulator
当你输入一个Lisp过程时
that when you read in a Lisp procedure
它们就会模拟那个过程所描述的程序
then those can simulate the program described by that, by that procedure.
所以解释器旨在成为一个通用模拟器
So the interpreter is worrying about making a general purpose simulator
而编译器 实际上
whereas the compiler, in effect,
只需要将东西配置成
is configuring the thing to be the machine
解释器将要去模拟的机器
that the interpreter would have been simulating.
所以编译器可以运行得更快
So the compiler can be faster.
另一方面
OK, On the other hand
解释器更适合用来排查错误
the interpreter is a nicer environment for debugging.
这是因为
And the reason for that is that we've got the
我们的源代码实际上就在那里
the source code actually there.
我们正在解释它们
We're interpreting it That's what we're working with.
并且库也在其中
And we also have the library around.
看 库是解释器的一部分
See, the interpreter--the library sitting there is part of the interpreter.
而编译器只会拉取
The compiler only pulls out from the library
运行程序所需要的代码
what it needs to run the program.
所以 如果你在排查错误的途中
So if you're in the middle of debugging
你想写一些额外的代码
and you might like to write a little extra program
来考察运行过程中的数据类型
to examine some run time data structure
或者做一些
or to produce some computation
在写程序时没有想到的计算
that you didn't think of when you wrote the program
解释器可以完美搞定这些
the interpreter can do that perfectly well
而编译器不行
whereas the compiler can't.
所以它们各有优点
So there are sort of dual, dual advantages.
编译器将生成运行更快的代码
The compiler will produce code that executes faster.
而解释器是一种更适合排错的环境
The interpreter is a better environment for debugging.
大多数Lisp系统最终将二者都实现了
And most Lisp systems end up having both
这样你就可以在开发阶段
end up being configured so you have an interpreter
可以使用解释器
that you use when you're developing your code.
随后通过编译加速代码的运行
Then you can speed it up by compiling.
并且通常
And very often,
你能够让被编译的代码
you can arrange that compiled code
和被解释的代码互相调用
and interpreted code can call each other.
我们将学习如何做到 其实不难
We'll see how to do that, That's not hard.
好
OK
事实上
In fact, the way we'll--
在我们将要构建的编译器中
in the compiler we're going to make
我们实现编译的代码和解释的代码
the way we'll arrange for compiled coding
互相调用的方式是
and interpreted code to call to call each other
我们让编译器和解释器使用
is that we'll have the compiler use exactly
使用完全一致的寄存器约定
the same register conventions as the interpreter.
编译器的理念
Well, the idea of a compiler
与解释器或求值器的理念很像
is very much like the idea of an interpreter or evaluator.
它们是相同的
It's the same thing.
求值器遍历代码
See, the evaluator walks over the code
产生一些寄存器操作
and performs some register operations.
就是我们昨天做的事情
That's what we did yesterday.
而编译器会读取代码
Well, the compiler essentially would like to walk over the code
生成一些求值器
and produce the register operations
在求值时会进行的
that the evaluator would have done
相关寄存器操作
were it evaluating the thing.
这就给我们提供了一个模型
And that gives us some model
来实现一个零阶编译器
for how to implement a zeroth-order compiler
一个很差劲但是能用的编译器
a very bad compiler but essentially a compiler.
这种模型就是
A model for doing that
你用求值器
is you just take the evaluator,
把代码跑一遍
you run it over the code
但不去执行实际的操作
but instead of executing the actual operations
只是把它们保存下来
you just save them away.
那就是你编译后的代码
And that's your compiled code.
让我举个例子
So let me give you an example of that.
假设我们要编译
Suppose we're going to compile--
编译(F X) 这个表达式
Suppose we want to compile the expression f of x.
我们假设
So let's assume that
EXP寄存器中保存着(F X)
we've got f of x in the exp register
而ENV寄存器又保存着其它东西
and something in the environment register.
想象我们启动了求值器
And now imagine starting up the evaluator.
它读取了表达式
Well, it looks at the expression
判断它是一个应用
and it sees that it's an application.
它分支到求值器代码中的一个地方
And it branches to a place in the
我们之前见过的叫EV-APPLICATION的地方
in the evaluator code we saw called ev-application.
然后继续处理
And then it begins.
#TBD
It stores away the operands and unev
然后之后它将运算符放在EXP寄存器中
and then it's going to put the operator in exp,
递归地对它求值
and it's going to go recursively evaluate it.
这就是我们经历的过程
That's the process that we walk through.
如果你看代码
And if you start looking at the code,
会看到一些寄存器操作
you start seeing some register operations.
你会看到将运算对象赋值给UNEV寄存器
You see assign to unev the operands
把运算符赋值给EXP
assign to exp the operator,
保存环境、生成新环境 等等
save the environment, generate that, and so on.
如果我们研究这里的性能开销
Well, if we look on the overhead here
会发现这些操作被生成出来
we can see those operations starting to be produced.
这是求值器实际要进行的
Here's sort of the first real operation
第一个操作
that the evaluator would have done.
它将运算对象从EXP寄存器里取出来
It pulls the operands out of the exp register
并将它赋值给UNEV
and assigns it to unev.
然后它给EXP寄存器赋了某个值
And then it assigns something to the expression register,
然后保存CONTINUE
and it saves continue
保存ENV
and it saves env.
我在这里就只是寄存器赋值
And all I'm doing here is writing down the register assignments
这就是求值器求值代码时进行的操作
that the evaluator would have done in executing that code.
我们缩小画面看看
And can zoom out a little bit.
总计有19个操作
Altogether, there are about 19 operations there.
这些代码
And this is the--this will be the piece of code
延续到
up until the point where
求值器跳转到APPLY-DISPATCH代码之前
the evaluator branches off to apply-dispatch.
事实上 在这个编译器中
And in fact, in this compiler
我们不需要再关心APPLY-DISPATCH了
we're not going to worry about apply-dispatch at all.
我们有所有东西
We're going to have everything
我们拥有解释后和编译后的所有代码
we're going to have both interpreted code and compiled code.
通常求值过程
Always evaluate procedures,
是由APPLY-DISPATCH处理的
always apply procedures by going to apply-dispatch.
这将让被解释后代码与编译后代码
That will easily allow interpreted code and
很容易互相调用
compiled code to call each other.
从原理上来说 这样做足矣
Well, in principle, that's all we need to do.
只需运行求值器
You just run the evaluator.
因而编译器非常像求值器
So the compiler's a lot like the evaluator.
你运行它 唯一不同是你把操作存下来
You run it, except it stashes away these operations
而不是实际执行它们
instead of actually executing them.
这其实不完全正确
Well, that's not, that's not quite true. there's
这里面我们撒了个小谎
There's only one little lie in that.
你需要关心的是：如果有个谓词
What you have to worry about is if you have a, a predicate.
如果你有某种测试需要做
If you have some kind of test you want to do
显然 在你编译时
obviously, at the point when you're compiling it
你不知道这些分支中
you don't know which branch of these--
哪条分支会被执行
of a conditional like this you're going to do.
所以你不能确定求值器将对哪个求值
So you can't say which one the evaluator would have done.
因此在这里就很简单
So all you do there is very simple.
你把两个分支全编译了
You compile both branches.
因此你编译出一个这样的结构
So you compile a structure that looks like this.
他们都会被编译成
That'll compile into something that says,
首先是P的代码
the code, the code for P.
它把结果存入VAL寄存器
And it puts its results in, say, the val register.
解释器对谓词求值
So you walk the interpreter over the predicate
并保证结果会放到VAL寄存器中
and make sure that the result would go into the val register.
随后你编译一条指令
And then you compile an instruction that says
如果VAL是TRUE
branch if, if val is true
就转到LABEL1这个地方
to a place we'll call label one.
然后我们写下B的代码
Then we, we will put the code for B
让解释器对B进行求值
to walk the interpreter--walk the interpreter over B.
然后写一句指令
And then go to put in an instruction that says,
GOTO NEXT THING
go to the next thing, whatever
就是它结束之后要去的地方
whatever was supposed to happen after this thing was done.
你放入那个指令
You put in that instruction.
这里你写下LABEL1
And here you put label one.
这里写A的代码
And here you put the code for A.
然后写下GOTO NEXT THING
And you put go to next thing.
这就是处理条件分支的办法
So that's how you treat a conditional.
你生成一小段这样的代码
You generate a little block like that.
除此之外
And other than that
编译器与求值器一模一样
this zeroth-order compiler is the same as the evaluator.
它只是把指令存起来 而不执行它们
It's just stashing away the instructions instead of executing them.
看起来很简单
That seems pretty simple,
但我们已经取得了某些收获
but we've gained something by that.
它会比求值器更有效率
See, already that's going to be more efficient than the evaluator.
因为 如果你观察求值器的运行
Because, if you watch the evaluator run
它并不只是进行寄存器操作
it's not only generating the register operations we wrote down
它还会决定执行哪个
it's also doing things to decide which ones to generate.
它做的第一件事就是
So the very first thing it does, say here
以它为例 就是进行某些测试
here for instance, is go do some tests
确定它是一个应用
and decide that this is an application
然后就跳转到
and then branch off to the place that,
处理应用的地方去
that handles applications.
换句话说 求值器做的事情是
In other words, what the evaluator's doing
分析代码需要进行的运算
is simultaneously analyzing the code to see what to do
同时并执行它们
and running these operations.
当你运行求值器一百万次
And when you-- if you run the evaluator a million times
这个分析过程就进行一百万次
that analysis phase happens a million times
而在编译器中 它只会进行一次
whereas in the compiler, it's happened once
之后就只有寄存器操作了
and then you just have the register operations themselves.
这就是零阶编译器了
Ok, that's a, a zeroth-order compiler
但它是个拙劣的编译器
but it is a wretched, wretched compiler.
它挺蠢的
It's really dumb.
让我们回过头来
Let's--let's go back and,
看看这张投影
and look at this overhead.
看看这个东西做的一些操作
So look at look at some of the operations this thing is doing.
我们想看看
We're supposedly
在解释(F  X)时的操作
looking at the operations in interpreting f of x.
这里就是它做了什么
Now, look here what it's doing.
举个例子 这里
For example, here
它将(OPERATOR (FETCH EXP))赋值给EXP
it assigns to exp the operator in fetch of exp.
其实没必要这样做
But see, there's no reason to do that, because this is--
因为编译器知道
the compiler knows
(OPERATOR (FETCH EXP))的值就是F
that the operator, fetch of exp,  is f right here.
因此这个指令没理由存在
So there's no reason why this instruction should say that.
应该改为：要把F赋值给EXP
It should say, we'll assign to exp, f.
或者实际上 你完全不需要EXP
Or in fact, you don't need exp at all.
没有理由需要EXP
There's no reason it should have exp at all.
EXP是用来做什么的?
What, what did exp get used for?
我们看这里
Well, if we come down here
我们对VAL赋值
we're going to assign to val
在环境里的EXP里寻找东西
look up the stuff in exp in the environment.
因此 我们实际上是要
So what we really should do
替换掉所有的EXP寄存器
get rid of the exp register altogether
把这个指令修改为
and just change this instruction to say,
给VAL赋值
assign to val
在环境中查找
look up the variable value
符号F的值
of the symbol f in the environment.
类似地
Similarly
回到这里 我们也完全不需要UNEV
back up here, we don't need unev at all
因为我们知道
because we know
因为我们知道 (FETCH EXP)取出的运算对象
what the operands of fetch of exp are for this piece of code.
就是'(X)
It's the, it's the list x.
从某种意义上来说
So in some sense
你完全不需要UNEV和EXP
you don't want unev and exp at all.
看看它们实际上是什么
See, what they really are in some sense,
它们不是它们实际运行机器的寄存器
those aren't registers of the actual machine that's supposed to run.
它们实际上是
Those are registers
为了模拟该机器的而设置的寄存器
that have to do with arranging the thing that can simulate that machine.
所以它们保存一些表达式
So they're always going to hold expressions
以编译器的视角看来 它们就是常量
which from the compiler's point of view, are just constants,
因此你可以把它们直接放到代码中
so can be put right into the code.
你可以忘掉那些关于
So you can forget about all the operations
EXP和UNEV的操作
worrying about exp and unev
只用那些常量
and just use those constants.
与之相似 如果我们回顾这里
Similarly, again, if we go, go back and look here
有像(ASSIGN CONTINUE EVAL-ARGS)之类的语句
there are things like assign to continue eval-args.
现在 它和任何东西都没有关系
Now, that has nothing to do with anything.
它只是求值器
That was just the evaluator
维护了下一步需要去哪
keeping track of where it should go next
在某些应用中对参数进行求值
to evaluate the arguments in some, in some application.
当然 这与编译器没关系
But of course, that's irrelevant to the compiler,
因为这个分析过程已经被编译器做完了
because you-- the analysis phase will have already done that.
所以编译后的代码完全不需要它
So this is completely irrelevant.
因此许多向CONTINUE寄存器
So a lot of these, these assignments
赋值的操作都是无用的
to continue have not to do
运行着的机器留着它们
where the running machine is supposed to continue
是为了跟踪它的状态
in keeping track of its state.
#TBD
It has to, to do with where the evaluator analysis should continue
而它们是完全无关的
and those are completely irrelevant.
因此我们可以去掉它们
So we can get rid of them.
那么 如果我们简单地
Ok, well, if we, if we simply do that,
进行这类优化
make those kinds of optimizations
不再考虑EXP和UNEV
get rid, get rid of worrying about exp and unev
去掉这些无关的寄存器赋值
and get rid of these irrelevant register assignments to continue
我们就可以找到这些代码
then we can take this literal code
也就是求值器会执行的这19条指令
these sort of 19 instructions that the evaluator would have done
给替换掉
and then replace them.
请看幻灯片
Let's look at the, at the slide.
我们去掉了大概一半
Replace them by--we get rid of about half of them.
同样 这就是某种过滤
And again, this is just sort of filtering
把无关的东西去掉
what the evaluator would have done by getting rid of the irrelevant stuff.
你们看 比如说
And you see, for instance
这里 求值器说
here the--where the evaluator said,
(ASSIGN VAL (LOOKUP 'F (FETCH ENV)))
assign val, look up variable value, fetch of exp
这里 我们放入了一个常量F
here we have put in the constant f.
这里又放了一个常量X
Here we've put in the constant x.
因此 这个编译器又稍微好一点
So there's a, there's a little better compiler.
但它还是比较蠢
It's still pretty dumb.
它仍会做很多蠢事
It's still doing a lot of dumb things.
我们再看幻灯片
Again, if we go look at the slide again
看最开头的地方
look at the very beginning here
我们调用(SAVE ENV)保存环境
we see a save the environment
然后给VAL寄存器赋某个值
assign something to the val register
然后恢复环境
and restore the environment.
它是从哪来的
Where'd that come from?
它来自求值器的这个地方
That came from the evaluator back here saying
哦 我在正在对一个应用求值
oh, I'm in the middle of evaluating an application.
因此我要递归调用EVAL-DISPATCH
So I'm going to recursively call eval dispatch.
我最好把接下来要用到的东西
So I'd better save the thing I'm going to need later,
保存到环境中
which is the environment.
这就是递归调用EVAL-DISPATCH的结果
This was the result of recursively calling eval dispatch.
刚才那个例子就是对符号F求值的结果
It was evaluating the symbol f in that case.
从EVAL-DISPATCH中返回
Then it came back from eval dispatch,
将环境恢复
restored the environment.
但是实际上
But in fact,
这个求值过程中 所进行的操作
the actual thing it ended up doing in the evaluation
完全不会影响环境
is not going to hurt the environment at all.
所以这里没必要先保存环境
So there's no reason to be saving the environment
再恢复环境
and restoring the environment here.
与之类似
Similarly
这里 我们保存了参数表
here I'm saving the argument list.
那是一个求值参数的循环
That's a piece of the argument evaluation loop,
先保存参数表
saving the argument list
然后在这里恢复
and here you restore it.
但事实上最后
But the actual thing that you ended up doing
并没有变更参数表
didn't trash the argument list.
所以不需要保存它
So there was no reason to save it.
换种方式来说
So another way to say, another way to say that
怎么说呢
is that the,
求值器需要最大限度地保持悲观
the evaluator has to be maximally pessimistic
因为 从它的视角来看
because as far from its point of view
只知道接下来是要对某些东西进行求值
it's just going off to evaluate something.
所以最好把稍后要用的都存下来
So it better save what it's going to need later.
一旦你完成了分析
But once you've done the analysis,
从编译器的角度就会考虑
the compiler is in a position to say
哪些是我真正需要存下来的?
well, what actually did I need to save?
我们需要去 --
And doesn't need to do any--
它不需要像求值器一样小心翼翼
it doesn't need to be as careful as the evaluator
因为它知道 实际需要什么
because it knows what it actually needs
无论如何 如果我们完成了优化
Well, in any case, if we do that
消除掉所有多余的保存和恢复
and eliminate all those redundant saves and restores
那么我们可以得到这样的结果
then we can get it down to this.
我们可以发现
And you see there are actually only three
只有三条指令是必须的
only three instructions that we actually need
从刚才的11条指令优化成这样
down from the initial 11 or so
或是从原始的20条指令优化而来
or the initial 20 or so in the original one.
这告诉我们
And that's just saying,
对于这些寄存器操作
of those register operations
哪些是必需的?
which ones did we actually need?
让我换个方式来总结一下
Let me just sort of summarize that in another way,
我先给你们看一张图
just to show you in a little better picture.
这个图片
Here's a picture of starting--
展示了所有的保存和恢复
This is looking at all the saves and restores.
这里是表达式(F X)
So here's the expression, f of x
在下面这里
and then this traces through, on the bottom here
是对求值器中各种地方的跟踪
the various places in the evaluator
在求值发生时会使用这些地方
that were passed when the evaluation happened.
在这里 你可以看到箭头
And then here, here you see arrows.
下箭头代表寄存器的保存
Arrow down means register saved.
所以最先发生的就是保存ENV
So the first thing that happened is the environment got saved.
然后 在这里恢复ENV
And over here, the environment got restored.
这些都是成对的栈操作
so there are all the pairs of stack operations.
如果你更进一步
Now, if you go ahead and say
我们记得
well, let's remember that we don't--that unev
UNEV是个完全没用的寄存器
for instance, is a completely useless register.
如果我们用固定结构的代码
And if we use the constant structure of the code
就不需要保存UNEV 因为完全用不上
well, we don't need, we don't need to save unev.
然后 根据我们约定的
And then, depending on how we set up the discipline of the--
调用过程应用的准则
of calling other things that apply,
我们会选择是否保存CONTINUE
we may or may not need to save continue.
这就是我们做的第一件事
That's the first step I did.
然后我们可以看看
And then we can look and see what's actually,
实际需要些什么
what's actually needed.
其实在求值F的过程中
See, we don't-- didn't really need to save env
我们不需要保存ENV
across-evaluating f
因为它不会被破坏
because it wouldn't, it wouldn't trash it.
因此 如果我们利用这点
So if we take advantage of that
这里对F的求值
and see the evaluation of f here
完全不需要担心
doesn't really need to worry about,
会破坏ENV
about hurting env.
类似地 这里对X的求值
And similarly, the evaluation of x here
当求值器进行求值时 它会说
when the evaluator did that it said
我最好保存好与之有关的函数寄存器
Oh, I'd better preserve the function register around that
因为后面也许会用得着
because I might need it later.
我最好也保存参数表
And I better preserve the argument list.
然而 在这如果是编译器的话
Whereas the compiler is now in a position to know
实际需要哪些寄存器
well, we didn't really need to save--
从而进行相关的保存与恢复
to do those saves and restores.
事实上 这里求值器做的所有栈操作
So in fact, all of the stack operations done by the evaluator
都证明是过于悲观而不必要
turned out to be unnecessary or overly pessimistic.
而编译器在这里是知道这一点的
And the compiler is in a position to know that.
这是最基础的想法
Well that's the basic idea.
我们把求值器
We take the evaluator
剔除那些不需要的东西
we eliminate the things that you don't need
去除那些对于编译器完全无用的东西
that in some sense have nothing to do with the compiler at all
只剩下求值器
just the evaluator
然后你可以看到哪些栈操作是不必要的
and then you see which stack operations are unnecessary.
这就是书中所描述的编译器
That's the basic structure of the compiler that's
的基本结构
that's described in the book.
我给你们展示一下这
Let me just show you how a
这个简单的例子
that examples a little bit too simple.
为了说清楚 多余的东西是怎样保存的
To see how you, how you actually save a lot
我们来看一个稍复杂的表达式
let's look at a little bit more complicated expression.
(F (G X) 1)
我们不会讲解所有的代码
And I'm not going to go through all the code.
因为代码有点多
There's a, there's a fair pile of it.
我认为在求值器在处理它时
I think there are, there are something like 16
大概会产生
16 pairs of register saves and restores
16对保存-恢复操作
as the evaluator walks through that.
这有一张图表
Here's a diagram of them.
演示了其中的过程
Let's see. You see what's going on.
你从这里开始--
You start out by--
求值器说：“我要求值一个应用”
the evaluator says, oh, I'm about to do an application.
在这里保存环境 又在这里恢复
I'll preserve the environment. I'll restore it here.
然后处理第一个运算对象
Then I'm about to do the first operand.
这是求值器的递归调用
Here it recursively goes to the evaluator.
求值器发现 这是一个应用
The evaluator says, oh, this is an application,
又会保存环境
I'll save the environment
求值组合式的运算符 然后在这里恢复环境
do the operator of that combination, restore it here.
这个恢复匹配的是这个保存操作
This save--this restore matches that save.
以此类推
And so on.
这里的UNEV
There's unev here,
完全没有必要存在
which turns out to be completely unnecessary
CONTINUE寄存器不断地被保存-恢复
continues getting bumped around here.
而FUN寄存器则是在
The function register is getting, getting saved
处理运算对象期间被保存
across the first operands, across the operands.
这类的事情一直在发生
All sorts of things are going on.
但如果你问 跟求值器相比
But if you say, well, what of those really were the business of
编译器究竟要做什么？
the compiler as opposed to the evaluator
你会去掉一大堆东西
you get rid of a whole bunch.
#TBD
And then on top of that, if you say things like
对F的求值不会修改ENV寄存器
the evaluation of F doesn't hurt the environment register,
或者对符号X的查找
or simply looking up the symbol X,
不需要对FUN寄存器做特别的保护
you don't have to protect the function register against that.
那你就得到了只有几对的保存-恢复操作
So you come down to just a couple of, a couple of pairs here.
然而 你还可以再优化一下
And still, you can do a little better.
看看这里的ENV寄存器发生了什么
Look what's going on here with the environment register.
我们观察ENV寄存器的操作 发现
The environment register comes along and says, oh,
这是一个组合式
here's a combination.
而这个求值器
This evaluator, by the way,
对G一无所知
doesn't know anything about G.
所以在这 它说
So here it says, so it says,
我最好保存ENV寄存器
I'd better save the environment register,
因为对G的求值
because evaluating G might be
可能会修改ENV寄存器的值
some arbitrary piece of code that would trash it
而我稍后可能会需要它
and I'm going to need it later,
在这个参数之后
after this argument,
在处理第二个参数的时候
for doing the second argument.
这就是为什么它没被优化掉
So that's why this one didn't go away,
因为编译器没有对G将要做的事情做任何假设
because the compiler made no assumptions about what G would do.
另一方面
On the other hand,
如果你看看这里的第二个参数
if you look at what the second argument is,
它只是查找“1”这个常量
that's just looking up one.
这不需要ENV寄存器
That doesn't need this environment register.
因此没必要保存它
So there's no reason to save it.
事实上 你也可以把这个也去掉
So in fact, you can get rid of that one, too.
这一堆寄存器操作
And from this whole pile of, of register operations,
如果你像这样简单地推理的话
if you simply do a little bit of reasoning like that,
只会剩下两对保存-恢复操作
you get down to, I think, just two pairs of saves and restores.
而这些 如果你知道关于G的某些信息的话
And those, in fact, could go away further if you,
可以进一步优化
if you knew something about G.
基本的理念是
So again, the general idea
编译器之所以更好
is that the reason the compiler can be better
是因为解释器对于将要处理的东西一无所知
is that the interpreter doesn't know what it's about to encounter.
它不得不以最悲观的方式保存东西
It has to be maximally pessimistic
来保护它自己
to protect itself.
而编译器
The compiler
只需要保存实际需要的东西
only has to deal with what actually had to be saved.
某个东西是否需要保存
And there are two reasons that something
有两种原因
might not have to be saved.
一种是
One is that
你保护的东西
what you're protecting it against,
不会修改寄存器
in fact, didn't trash the register,
例如 变量查找
like it was just a variable look-up.
另一种原因是
And the other one is,
你所保存的东西
that the thing that you were saving it for
最后并不会被用到
might turn out not to actually need it.
因此 编译器正是利用了
So those are the two basic pieces of knowledge
这两条基本原则
that the compiler can take advantage of
来让代码变得更高效的
in making the code more efficient.
有什么问题吗？
Let's break for questions.
学生: 你一直在说UNEV寄存器
AUDIENCE: You kept saying that the uneval register,
UNEV寄存器完全不会被用到
unev register didn't need to be used at all.
是否意味着 机器只需要6个寄存器足矣？
Does that mean that you could just map a six-register machine?
或者是说 在这个特定的例子里
Or is that, in this particular example,
它没有被用到？
it didn't need to be used?
教授: 对于编译器
PROFESSOR: For the compiler,
你可以生成6个或5个寄存器的代码
you could generate code for the six-register, five, right?
因为EXP寄存器也没有用到
Because that exp goes away also.
是的 你可以把EXP和UNEV都去掉
Assuming--yeah, you can get rid of both exp and unev
因为这些是求值器的数据结构
because, see, those are data structures of the evaluator.
以编译器的视角来看
Those are all things that would be constants
这些东西都是常量
from the point of view of the compiler.
关键在于
The only thing is
这个特定编译器是被构造出来的
this particular compiler is set up
因此被解释的代码和被编译的代码可以共存
so that interpreted code and compiled code can coexist.
可以这样看待它
So the way to think about it is,
你构建了一个芯片
is maybe you build a chip
它就是求值器
which is the evaluator,
而编译器可以做的就是
and what the compiler might do
为这个芯片生成代码
is generate code for that chip.
只是它不会用到两个寄存器而已
It just wouldn't use two of the registers.
好 休息一会
All right, let's take a break.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
我们刚才研究了编译器应该要做什么
We just looked at what the compiler is supposed to do.
现在我们来简略地看看
Now let's very briefly look at how,
这些目标如何达成
how this gets accomplished.
而我不会给出细节
And I'm going to give no details.
在书中有一大堆代码
There's, there's a giant pile of code in the book
展示了所有细节
that gives all the details.
我要做的 是给你们展示
But what I want to do is just show you the,
其中的关键思想
the essential idea here.
换个时间再来关心细节
Worry about the details some other time.
设想我们正在编译一条表达式
Let's imagine that we're compiling an expression
这里有一些运算符
that looks like there's some operator
和两个参数
and there are two arguments.
现在
Now, the--
这个编译器会生成什么代码?
what's the code that the compiler should generate?
首先
Well, first of all,
它会递归运行
it should recursively go off
编译运算符
and compile the operator.
它说 我要编译运算符
So it says, I'll compile the operator.
最后我需要让它们的结果
And where I'm going to need that
存放在FUN寄存器中
is to be in the function register, eventually.
所以我编译一些指令
So I'll compile some instructions
它们会编译运算符
that will compile the operator
最后把结果放在FUN寄存器中
and end up with the result in the function register.
接下来我要做的是
The next thing it's going to do,
另一个代码片段则说
another piece is to say,
我要编译第一个参数
I have to compile the first argument.
因此它递归调地用自己
So it calls itself recursively.
而结果会被放在VAL中
And let's say the result will go into val.
接下来需要做的是
And then what it's going to need to do is
建立起参数表
start setting up the argument list.
(ASSIGN ARGL (CONS (FETCH --
So it'll say, assign to argl cons of fetch--
#TBD
so it generates this literal instruction--
(FETCH VAL) '()))
fetch of val onto empty list.
然而
However,
当它到这里时
it might have to work--  when it gets here,
它可能需要环境
it's going to need the environment.
它需要环境
It's going to need whatever environment was here
这是求值第一个参数所需要的
in order to do this evaluation of the first argument.
因此 它需要保证
So it has to ensure that
对运算对象的编译
the compilation of this operand,
或者说它需要保护FUN寄存器
or it has to protect the function register
来应对编译运算对象时发生的各种情况
against whatever might happen in the compilation of this operand.
因此它在这做了个标记说
So it puts a note here and says, oh,
这个片段需要保护ENV寄存器
this piece should be done preserving the environment register.
与之类似 这里
Similarly, here,
在完成第一个运算对象的编译后
after it gets done compiling the first operand,
它会说 我最好--
it's going to say, I'd better--
我需要知道第二个运算对象的环境
I'm going to need to know the environment for the second operand.
所以它在这做了个标记
So it puts a little note here, saying,
这里也需要保护ENV
yeah, this is also done preserving env.
现在它继续运行
Now it goes on and says, well,
下一段代码
the next chunk of code
是要编译第二个参数
is the one that's going to compile the second argument.
它将会
And let's say
把编译的结果按约定放入到VAL中
And let's say it'll compile it with a targeted to val, as they say.
随后它会生成一条指令
And then it'll generate the literal instruction,
从而建立起参数表
building up the argument list.
(ASSIGN ARGL
So it'll say, assign to argl
(CONS (FETCH VAL) ( FETCH ARGL))
cons of the new value it just got onto the old argument list.
然而
However,
为了取得旧的参数表
in order to have the old argument list,
它最好保证这期间发生的任何事情
it better have arranged that the argument list didn't get trashed
都不影响旧的参数表
by whatever happened in here.
因此它在这做了个标注说
So it puts a little note here and says,
哦 这里需要保护ARGL
oh, this has to be done preserving argl.
现在参数表就建立好了
Now it's got the argument list set up.
现在可以准备去APPLY-DISPATCH了
And it's all ready to go to apply dispatch.
它生成了这条指令
It generates this literal instruction.
因为现在参数都在ARGL中
Because now it's got the arguments in argl
运算符在FUN中
and the operator in fun,
等一下 它只在FUN中用到运算符#TBD
but wait, it's only got the operator in fun
如果它已经保证这块代码
if it had ensured that this block of code
不会破坏FUN寄存器里的东西
didn't trash what was in the function register.
所以它在这做了个标注
So it puts a little note here and says,
这里的所有东西
oh, yes, all this stuff here
最好能够在保护FUN寄存器的情况下完成
had better be done preserving the function register.
#TBD
So that's the little--so when it starts ticking--
基本上来说
so basically, what the
编译器所做的就是
what the compiler does is
追加一大堆的代码
append a whole bunch of code sequences.
而这些代码之中都是一些基本运算
See, what it's got in it is little primitive pieces of things
比如符号查找
like how to look up a symbol,
条件分支的处理
how to do a conditional.
都是一些琐碎的事情
Those are all little pieces of things.
然后它按照这种准则将它们追加到一起
And then it appends them together in this sort of discipline.
因此 组合的基本手段就是
So the basic means of combining things
将一段代码追加到另一段的后面
is to append two code sequences.
就是这里发生的事情
That's what's going on here.
这有点取巧
And it's a little bit tricky.
思路就是 追加两段代码
The idea is that it appends two code sequences,
小心保护寄存器
taking care to preserve a register.
追加操作看起来像这样
So the actual append operation looks like this.
它要做的是
What it wants to do is say, if--
代码的追加是这么来做的
here's what it means to append two code sequences.
如果SEQ1需要寄存器--
So if sequence one needs register--
我应该改一下这个
I should change this.
在SEQ1后面追加SEQ2
Append sequence one to sequence two,
并保护一些寄存器
preserving some register.
这里改成AND
Let me say, and.
这样的话前后顺序就清楚了
So it's clear that sequence one comes first.
如果SEQ2需要寄存器
So if sequence two needs the register
而SEQ1又修改了寄存器
and sequence one modifies the register,
那么编译器生成的指令是
then the instructions that the compiler spits out,
保存寄存器
are save the register.
这就是代码
Here's the code.
你生成了这段代码
You generate this code.
保存寄存器
Save the register,
然后写下递归编译SEQ1的结果
and then you put out the recursively compiled stuff for sequence one.
然后你恢复寄存器
And then you restore the register.
然后写下递归编译
And then you put out the recursively compiled stuff
SEQ2的结果
for sequence two.
这就是你需要做的
That's in the case where you need to do it.
实际上SEQ2需要寄存器
Sequence two actually needs the register,
而SEQ1改动了它
and sequence one actually clobbers it.
否则的话
So that's sort of if. Otherwise,
得到的就是SEQ1后面跟着SEQ2
all you spit out is sequence one followed by sequence two.
这就是把两个代码片段
So that's the basic operation
连接到一起的基本操作
for sticking together these bits of code fragments,
#TBD
these bits of instructions into a sequence.
从这个角度看
And you see, from this point of view,
解释器和编译器的区别
the difference between the interpreter and the compiler, in some sense,
是编译器有保护寄存器的标注
is that where the compiler has these preserving notes,
上面记录着
and says, maybe I'll actually generate the
是否需要生成保存-恢复代码
saves and restores and maybe I won't,
而解释器会以最悲观的方式处理
the interpreter being maximally pessimistic
总是会进行保存-恢复
always has a save and restore here.
这就是关键的区别
That's the essential difference.
为了实现这个
Well, in order to do this, of course,
编译器需要一些理论
the compiler needs some theory of
来确定代码序列会修改哪些寄存器
what code sequences need and modifier registers.
所以你放入的小片段
So the tiny little fragments that you put in, like
例如这段基础代码
the basic primitive code fragments,
当你查找一个变量时
say, what are the operations that you do
进行了哪些操作？
when you look up a variable?
你又是做了些什么
What are the sequence of things that you do
来编译一个常量
when you compile a constant
或者应用一个函数
or apply a function?
它们都会带有一些标注
Those have little notations in there
说明了它们需要的寄存器 和修改的寄存器
about what they need and what they modify.
所以底层的数据结构
So the bottom-level data structures--
我会这样讲
Well, I'll say this.
传递给编译器的代码序列大概是这样
A code sequence to the compiler looks like this.
它里面有实际的指令序列
It has the actual sequence of instructions.
跟它一起的还有
And then, along with it,
一组被修改的寄存器
there's the set of registers modified.
还有一组需要的寄存器
And then there's the set of registers needed.
为了能够执行此操作
So that's the information the compiler has
编译器必须要掌握这些信息
that it draws on in order to be able to do this operation.
它们从哪来呢
And where do those come from? Well.
它们来自于--你们可能也想到了
Well, those come from, you might expect,
对于那些最基本的片段
for the very primitive ones,
我们会手工添加
we're going to put them in by hand.
然后 当我们组合两个序列时
And then, when we combine two sequences,
我们会计算出这两个集合
we'll figure out what these things should be.
举一个非常基本的例子
So for example, a very primitive one, let's see.
例如做一个寄存器赋值
How about doing a register assignment.
因此 基本代码片段会说
So a primitive sequence might say,
噢 它是个代码片段
oh, it's code fragment.
代码的指令部分是(ASSIGN R1 (FETCH R2))
Its code instruction is assigned to R1, fetch of R2.
这个例子就是这样的
So this is an example.
这就是指令序列的一个例子
That might be an example of a sequence of instructions.
和它在一起的是
And along with that, it'll say, Oh
它需要记得修改了R1
oh, what I need to remember is that that modifies R1
然后它需要R2
and then it needs R2.
因此当你开始构建编译器时
So when you're first building this compiler,
你放入这样的一个片段
you put in little fragments of stuff like that.
当它组合两个序列时
And now, when it combines two sequences,
我要组合
if I'm going to combine,
代码片段S1
let's say, sequence one,
修改了一组寄存器M1
that modifies a bunch of registers M1,
并且需要一组寄存器N1
and needs a bunch of registers N1.
并且我要把它和序列S2组合到一起
And I'm going to combine that with sequence two.
它修改了一组寄存器M2
That modifies a bunch of registers M2,
并且需要一组寄存器N2
and needs a bunch of registers N2.
这样我们就能得出结果
Then, well, we can reason it out.
新的代码片段是这样的
The new code fragment,
指令序列S1后面跟着S2
sequence one, and-- followed by sequence two,
它要修改什么?
well, what's it going to modify?
它要修改的是
The things that it will modify are the things
被S1修改
that are modified either by
以及又被S2修改的寄存器
sequence one or sequence two.
N1和N2的并集 就是了新的修改集
So the union of these two sets are what the new thing modifies.
然后你问
And then you say, well, what is this--
哪些寄存器是需要的？
what registers is it going to need?
需要这些寄存器的是
It's going to need the things that are,
首先 一定是序列S1需要的
first of all, needed by sequence one.
因此必然有N1
So what it needs is sequence one.
然后 并不是N2里面的所有元素
And then, well, not quite all of the ones
我们都需要
that are needed by sequence two.
新的修改集需要N2中那些
What it needs are the ones that are needed by sequence two
没有被S1修改过的寄存器
that have not been set up by sequence one.
所以 这个并集是N1并上
So it's sort of the union of
序列S2的需要集N2
the things that sequence two needs
序列S1的修改集M1
minus the ones that sequence one modifies.
因为它关心的是#TBD
Because it worries about setting them up.
这就是编译器的基本结构
So there's the basic structure of the compiler.
寄存器优化的方式是
The way you do register optimizations is you
你用一些策略来应对需要保护的东西
you have some strategies for what needs to be preserved.
这取决于数据结构
That depends on a data structure.
这取决于将东西组合在一起的操作
Well, it depends on the operation of what it means to put things together.
想知道要保护哪些东西
Preserving something, that depends on  knowing
就需要知道这段代码需要以及修改的寄存器
what registers are needed and modified by these code fragments.
这就需要我们有一个数据结构
That depends on having little data structures,
它不但要存放实际的指令序列
which say, a code sequence is the actual instructions,
它修改了什么 又需要什么
what they modify and what they need.
这些信息来自于--最基本的情况是内置的
That comes from, at the primitive level, building it in.
对于最基本的情况
At the primitive level,
我们可以容易地知道
it's going to be completely obvious
需要哪些寄存器 又修改了哪些
what something needs and modifies.
另外
Plus,
利用这个特定的方法构建复杂指令时
this particular way that says, when I build up bigger ones,
我们可以像这样生成新的修改集
here's how I generate the new set of registers modified
以及新的需要集
and the new set of registers needed.
这就是全部的内容 -- 我不该这么说
And that's the whole-- well, I shouldn't say that's the whole thing.
这就是书里面大概30页的细节
That's the whole thing except for about
的核心内容了
about 30 pages of details in the book.
但它是一个完全可用的初级编译器
But it is a perfectly usable rudimentary compiler.
让我给你展示一下它能做什么
Let me kind of show you what it does.
假设我们从一个递归阶乘开始
Suppose we start out with recursive factorial.
这些幻灯片的字太小不适合阅读
And these slides are going to be much too small to read.
我只想快速翻一下代码
I just want to flash through the code
让你们看看它有多少代码
and show you about how much it is.
代码从这开始--
That starts out with--
这是代码的第一部分
here's a first block of it,
这里编译了一个过程入口
where it compiles a procedure entry
并进行了一些赋值操作
and does a bunch of assignments.
这基本上对应了解释器中
And this thing is basically up through the part where
进行判断之前的部分
sets up to do the predicate
并判断谓词是否成立
and test whether the predicate's true.
第二部分是
The second part
递归调用N-1的阶乘的结果
is what results from-- in the recursive call to fact of n minus one.
最后一部分是
And this last part
从那里返回
is coming back from that
并处理递归的基本情况
and then taking care of the constant case.
这就是编译阶乘会生成的代码量
So that's about how much code it would produce for factorial.
当然 我们可以把这个编译器做得更好
We could make this compiler much, much better, of course.
优化它的主要方式是
The main way we could make it better is
当你调用一个过程时
to allow the compiler to make any assumptions at all
允许编译器做任何假设
about what happens when you call a procedure.
举例来说
So this compiler, for instance,
这个编译器甚至不知道
doesn't even know, say, that multiplication
乘法可以被内联执行
you say, is something that could be coded in line.
它则会自行构建起整个机制
Instead, it sets up this whole mechanism.
进行APPLY-DISPATCH
It goes to apply-dispatch.
这是极大的浪费
That's a tremendous waste,
因为 每当你进行APPLY-DISPATCH时
because what you do every time you go to apply-dispatch
你都要关心这个参数表
is you have to concern about this argument list,
因为它是个很普遍的操作
because it's a very general thing you're going to.
在任何真实的编译器中
In any real compiler, of course,
你会有寄存器来暂存参数
you're going to have registers for holding arguments.
你要开始保护
And you're going to start preserving
保存这些寄存器
saving the way you use those registers
和这里的策略相近
similar to the same strategy here.
因此 我们可能主要通过这个方法
So that's probably the very main way
来优化书中这个特定的编译器
this particular compiler in the book could be fixed.
还有其它的一些方法
There are other things like
比如查找变量的值
looking up variable values and
使用更高效的基本操作等等
making more efficient primitive operations, and all sorts of things.
比如查找变量的值
looking up variable values and
使用更高效的基本操作等等
making more efficient primitive operations, and all sorts of things.
本质上来说 一个好的Lisp编译器可以吸收任意数量的努力
Essentially, a good Lisp compiler can absorb an arbitrary amount of effort.
可能这其中的一个原因是
And probably one of the reasons
跟FORTRAN比
Lisp is slow
Lisp就比这类语言要慢
with compared to languages like FORTRAN
如果你回头审视历史
is that, if you look over history
会发现人们为构建Lisp编译器而呕心沥血
the amount of effort that's gone into building Lisp compilers,
但也远远没有接近构建FORTRAN编译器的工作量
it's nowhere near the amount of effort that's gone into FORTRAN compilers.
在接下来的几年
And maybe that's something that will
情况可能会发生变化
that will change over the next couple of years.
好吧 就讲到这里
OK, let's break.
有问题吗
Questions?
学生: 很早的一个课时里--
AUDIENCE: One of the very first classes--
我不记得是课上还是课后--
I don't know if it was during class or after class-
你向我们展示了
you showed me the, the
ADD操作有一些我们看不到的基本运算
say, addition has a primitive that we don't see,
类似于ADD%之类的
and-percent add or something like that.
这是因为
Is that because,
你想把代码内联为
if you're doing inline code
专门针对二元运算对象的运算么？
you'd want to just do it for two operators, operands?
但如果你有更多操作运算对象
But if you had more operands,
你会做什么特殊的事情吗？
you'd want to do something special?
教授: 你看的是Scheme的实际实现
PROFESSOR: Yeah, you're looking in the actual scheme implementation.
其中有一个‘+’ 这是一个运算符
There's a plus, and a plus is some operator.
如果你看‘+’的源代码
And then if you go look inside the code for plus,
你会看到一些叫做--
you see something called--
我记不清了--可能叫ADD%、PLUS之类的东西
I forget-- and-percent plus or something like that.
这里所进行的
And what's going on there is
就是你说得那种优化
is that particular kind of optimization.
因为 通常‘+’接受任意数量的参数
Because, see, general plus takes an arbitrary number of arguments.
所以 最一般性的加法
So the most general plus
会说：如果我有一个参数表
says, oh, if I have an argument list,
我最好将它们用CONS连接到表里
I'd better cons it up in some list
并指出有多少个参数
and then figure out how many there were or something like that.
这样的效率非常差
That's terribly inefficient,
因为大部分时间你在把两个数相加
especially since most of the time you're probably adding two numbers.
你不必把整个参数表连接到一起
You don't want to really have to cons this argument list.
所以你想做的是
So what you'd like to do is build
构建把一堆东西相加的代码
the code for plus with a bunch of entries.
所以它做的大部分事情是一样的
So most of what it's doing is the same.
但这里可能有个特殊的入口
However, there might be a special entry
如果你知道只有两个参数
that you'd go to if you knew there were only two arguments.
你会把它们放到寄存器中
And those you'll put in registers.
它们不在参数表里
they won't be in an argument list
你也不必用CONS连接它们
and you won't have to CONS.
这就是这些东西工作的原理
That's how a lot of these things work.
好吧 下课吧
OK, let's take a break.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]